Finding Aid for Seth K. Shetterly papers, 1829-1934
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Seth K. Shetterly papers 1829-1934
Shetterly, Seth K., b. 1820.
1 oversize folders
2 linear feet
8623 Aa 2; Ac
Utica, Michigan attorney, justice of the peace, and state representative. Correspondence mainly concerning family, legal, and political affairs; also scattered municipal and township records, 1846-1865, for Utica and Shelby and Sterling townships in Macomb County, Michigan, especially school records; and miscellaneous business and legal papers, poems, essays, and notebooks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Shetterly papers were donated by Arthur Van Duren (donor no. 988 ) in 1939.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Seth K. Shetterly, Utica, Michigan, pioneer, lawyer, and politician, was born October 15, 1820 in Union County, Pennsylvania. His parents came to Michigan in August 1832, and he obtained his elementary education in the district schools. In 1840, his father moved to Ann Arbor, and Seth entered the law office of Miles, Ramsdett, and Wilson. He was admitted to the bar in 1843, and in June 1844 opened a law office at Utica. He was married in 1843 to Harriet H. Wright who died in 1849. He was married again in 1853 to Amelia Sterns who died in 1858. In 1859, he married Clara A. Wright to whom he remained married until his own death, probably around 1893.
Shetterly also held numerous political offices. He was elected Justice of the Peace in April 1854, a position he held throughout his life. In 1862, he was elected Circuit Court Commissioner for Macomb County, and reelected in 1864. In 1867, he was elected to the Michigan Legislature from the southern district of Macomb County and in 1876 from the western district. In 1846, he was appointed a Master in Chancery by Governor Barry. Shetterly was also a member of the Masonic order.
The papers of Seth K. Shetterly cover the years 1835-1934 though the bulk of the material falls between 1850 and 1890. The papers are arranged into four series: Correspondence, Municipal and Township Records, Miscellaneous Papers, and Diaries and Ledgers.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Michigan State Normal School.; Grand Traverse Bay Region (Mich.); Justices of the peace--Michigan--Macomb County.; Lawyers--Michigan--Utica.; Macomb County (Mich.); Macomb County (Mich.)--Schools.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1815-1844.; Niles (Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Macomb County.; Shelby (Macomb County, Mich.: Township); Sterling Heights (Mich.); Utica (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--To 1837.
Contributors:
Adams, Edward Francis, 1839-1939.; Aldrich, R. J.; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.; Clark, George Brownell.; Dickinson, Donald McDonald, 1846-1917.; Douglas, Silas H. (Silas Hamilton), 1816-1890.; Duffield, D. Bethune (Divie Bethune), 1821-1891.; Eldridge, James B.; Lowell, Dwight Nelson, d. 1907.; Pitcher, Zina, 1797-1872.; Stephen, John.; Stephens, James.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically from 1829 to 1934. It is by far the largest series, measuring ten linear inches. The series consists mostly of the professional and personal correspondence of Seth Shetterly. In addition to family members, correspondents include R.J. Aldrich, Zachariah Chandler, George Brownell Clark, Don McDonald Dickinson, Silas Hamilton Douglas, David Bethune Duffield, James B. Eldridge, D.N. Lowell, Zina Pitcher, John Stephens, and James Stephens. There is also some correspondence of other persons. In the folders covering the years 1829-1848, most of the correspondence is Samuel Smith's of Oakland County, Michigan. Included are several letters written 1834-1835 by his son while serving in the Army at Fort Gibson [present day Oklahoma]. He describes the high mortality rate and low morale at the fort. The last folder of correspondence, 1898-1934, consists almost entirely of the correspondence of Seth's widow Clara, mostly letters from her children.
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1829-1836 (Box 1)
    (include letter, September 29, 1834, containing a description of Niles, Michigan)
  - 1838-1848 (Box 1)
  - 1849-1852 (Box 1)
  - 1853-1854 (Box 1)
  - 1855-1857 (Box 1)
    (include letter, December 18, 1857, from Silas H. Douglas; also letter, December 8, 1857, from Zina Pitcher)
  - 1858-March 1859 (Box 1)
    (include letter, January 12, 1858, from Zachariah Chandler)
  - April 1859-August 1859 (Box 1)
  - September 1859-August 1860 (Box 1)
  - September 1860-1861 (Box 1)
  - 1862-March 1864 (Box 1)
  - April 1864-1867 (Box 1)
    (include letter, October 31, 1866, from James B. Eldridge)
  - January-June 1868 (Box 1)
  - July 1868-1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870-1872 (Box 1)
  - 1873 (Box 1)
  - 1874 (Box 1)
    (include letter from James Eldridge)
  - 1875 (Box 1)
  - 1876-February 1877 (Box 1)
  - March-August 1877 (Box 1)
    (include letter, March 17, 1876, from Donald M. Dickinson)
  - September-December 1877 (Box 1)
  - 1878 (Box 1)
  - 1879 (Box 1)
  - 1880 (Box 1)
  - January-October 1881 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1881 (Box 1)
  - 1882 (Box 1)
  - January-September 1883 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1883 (Box 1)
  - 1884 (Box 1)
  - 1885 (Box 1)
  - 1886 (Box 1)
  - 1887-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890-1893 (Box 1)
  - 1898-1934 (Box 1)
    (only two items after 1912)
- Municipal and Township Records
  Municipal and Township Records consists of almost two linear inches of poll lists and school records from Utica and Shelby and Sterling Townships in Macomb County. Although the poll lists are undated, the school records run from 1846 to 1865. Included in the school records are essays, lesson plans, tax bills, bonds, teacher contracts, papers on building a school house, by-laws, business papers, and circulars from the state superintendent of public instruction.
  - Poll Lists and Members of the Cleveland and Hendrick Club undated (Box 1)
  - Sterling and Shelby Schools
    - Essays in science and history (Box 1)
    - School papers (mostly algebra lessons) (Box 1)
    - School taxes, rate bills 1862-1863 (Box 1)
    - School bonds 1861-1865 (Box 1)
    - Teachers contracts 1859-1862 (Box 1)
    - School District No. 1
      - Administrative 1859-1864 (Box 1)
        (papers on building a school house, by-laws, and treasurer's bond)
      - Receipts, accounts payable, and miscellaneous 1859-1864, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - School District No. 2 1846-1858 (Box 1)
      (mostly circulars from state superintendent of public instruction)
  - Printed Items: printed items from Utica area and 1861 Michigan law requiring municipal officials to record vital statistics (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous Papers consists of four linear inches, made up mostly of legal papers and receipts and accounts payable. There is also a folder of printed items from the Utica area including posters, advertisements, and political notices.
  - Miscellaneous: includes Shetterly's remarks on Gospel of Mark and printed items (Box 1)
  - Legal Papers, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Receipts and Accounts Payable 1832-1889, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Bills of Lading 1856 (Box 2)
  - Magazines 1889 (single issues of Arthur's Home Magazine and Peterson's Magazine) (Box 2)
- Diaries and Ledgers
  Diaries and Ledgers consists of eleven volumes running from 1850 to 1875. Most are business diaries ledgers, but three volumes are personal diaries.
  - 1850-1851 (pocket ledger) (Box 2)
  - 1853 (business diary) (Box 2)
  - 1855 (business diary) (Box 2)
  - 1856-1862 (unbound personal daily journal) (Box 2)
  - 1863 (business diaries), 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1864 (business diary) (Box 2)
  - 1865 (business diary) (Box 2)
  - 1870 (ledger) (Box 2)
  - 1872 (personal diary) (Box 2)
  - 1875 (personal diary) (Box 2)
  - Undated circa 1854 (ledger) (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Deeds and land grants 1835-1863, 13 items (Folder 1)